A Guide to the Achilles James Tynes Letters, 1864-1951
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Achilles James Tynes Letters, 1864-1951
Library of Virginia
27936
159 leaves, negative photostats
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Harriet Louisa Tynes, 1009 Carolina Street, Greensboro, North Carolina, 23 March 1972. Originals owned by A. Lacy Tynes of Leesburg, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Achilles James Tynes was born 29 November 1833 in Montgomery County, Virginia, to Smuel Tynes (1811-1879) and Frances Herndon Haythe Tynes (1812-1869). Tynes moved to Tazewell County, Virginia, from Roanoke County, Virginia, in 1857. When the Civil War began, Tynes enlisted in the 8th Virginia Cavalry 25 July 1861, helping to form Company H. Appointed a captain 15 May 1862, he served until the end of the war and was paroled 22 May 1865 in Charleston, West Virginia. After the war, Tynes returned to Tazewell County to farm. He established a woolen mill factory in the county and also helped establish the county's public schools. He served as president of the Tazewell Street Railway Company which brought electricity to the county. Tynes married Harriet Louisa Fudge (1842-1922) 2 March 1864, and they had eleven children. Tynes died 11 November 1914 in Tazewell County.
Scope and Content
Letters, 1864-1951, of Achilles J. Tynes (1833-1914) of Tazewell County, Virginia, to his wife Harriet Louisa Fudge Tynes (1842-1922) discussing military life, including campaigns in southwest Virginia, the Shenandoah Valley, and West Virginia. He describes various fights, including the battles of Lynchburg, 3rd Winchester, Fisher's Hill, Cedar Creek, and Waynesboro. He comments on various Confederate generals such as Robert E. Lee (1807-1870), John McCausland (1836-1927), Albert Gallatin Jenkins (1830-1864), Jubal Early (1816-1894), Thomas Rosser (1836-1910), Lunsford Lindsey Lomax (1835-1913), and Fitzhugh Lee (1835-1905), and their Union army counterparts Ulysses S. Grant (1822-1885), George Crook (1828-1890), William Averell (1832-1900), David Hunter (1802-1886), and Philip Sheridan (1831-1888). Tynes details his day-to-day activities and offers advice to his wife regarding the homefront difficulties she faces during the war. Also includes a letter to his father Samuel Tynes (1811-1879) concerning the war. Also contains a letter, 15 September 1910, from William S. Grimes concerning Toland's Raid and the 26th Virginia Infantry Battalion. Also includes letter, 1 November 1950, from W. Edwin Hemphill (1912-) of the Virginia State Library to Buford C. Tynes (1884-1954) of Huntingdon, West Virginia, concerning the ride of Molly Tynes (1837-1891) to alert inhabitants of Tazewell County about Toland's Raid, and Tynes' reply to Hemphill, 3 November 1950. Also includes a letter, 15 May 1951, from Buford C. Tynes to Achilles L. Tynes (1873-1952) of Staunton, Virginia, regarding the Kanawha Valley during the Civil War.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Edwin H. Harman, Letters, 1860-1864 (LVA accession 27935)
Historic Crab Orchard Museum papers, [1598?]-1922 (LVA accession 34648)
Contents List
- Letters, 17 May 1864-18 June 1864 (Folder 1)
  - Letter, 17 May 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Jenkins' Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Louisa Fudge Tynes, Tazewell County, Virginia, sending camp news including a skirmish troops had with Union troops and the capture of prisoners., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 24 May 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Jenkins Cavalry, to Harriet Tynes informing her of the death of General Albert Gallatin Jenkins, the movements of the Union army under Generals Averell and Crook, and other camp news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 27 May 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Jenkins Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Tynes discussing Confederate and Union troop movements. He mentions his health and concern over her wellbeing., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 3 June 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes commenting on camp and personal news. Tynes expresses concern about his wife's health., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 4 June 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, 5th Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Tynes describing a skirmish between Confederate and Union forces in Alleghany County, near Covington and mentioning other military manouvers. He also sends personal and camp news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 13 June 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, 5th Cavalry Brigade, Rockbridge County, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes commenting on the movements of troops now located in Rockbridge County. He describes camp life., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 14 June 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes describing a fight between Confederate and Union troops that he is in., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 14 June 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Bedford County, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes regarding fighting in the Shenandoah Valley between Confederate troops and Union troops., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 18 June 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, [Lynchburg, Virginia], to Harriet Tynes describing the battle of Lynchburg between Confederate troops under the command of General Jubal Early and Union troops under the command of General David Hunter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letters, 22 June 1864-10 August 1864 (Folder 2)
  - Letter, 22 June 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Early's Army Corps, to Harriet Tynes discussing the pursuit by General Early's Confederate troops of Union forces under General Hunter., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 27 June 1864, Achilles J. Tynes, Staunton, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes concerning the pursuit of Union troops. He also comments on life in camp and gives her an account of his business concerns., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 4 July 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Rosser's Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Tynes commenting on Jubal Early's Maryland Campaign in the summer of 1864., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 18 July 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, 5th Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Tynes commenting on the 1864 Maryland campaign and discussing personal and family business., 10 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 18 July 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, 5th Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Tynes concerning the theft of horses from camp and other camp news., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 21 July 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, 5th Cavalry Brigade, Warren County, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes commenting on camp life and mentioning fighting in the Shenandoah Valley., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 25 July 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes commenting on camp life and fighting in the Shenandoah Valley., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 28 July 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, 5th Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Tynes discussing the current campaign, noting that he is leaving his baggage behind on the move, and stating there was a false alarm of a Union army attack., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 29 July 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes informing her of the movement of Early's army across the Potomac River into Maryland and Pennsylvania and sending news of the campaign., 12 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 10 August 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, McCausland's Brigade, to Harriet Tynes describing a fight in the Shenandoah Valley, commenting on the campaign, and sending other news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letters, 30 August 1864-26 October 1864 (Folder 3)
  - Letter, 30 August 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes stating that he has visited relatives in the area where he is now camped and sends news of them. He also expresses concern about her wellbeing., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 19 September 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Woodstock, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes sending news of the defeat of Early's army at the 3rd battle of Winchester. Includes a note that he has a new horse., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 24 September 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes describing the fighting between Confederates under General Early and Union troops under General Philip Sheridan, including the battle of Fisher's Hill., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 26 September 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Albemarle County, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes lamenting the string of Confederate defeats and fulminating against a lack of discipline in the army., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 30 September 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Nelson County, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes sending news of friends in the area and informing her of fighting between Early's troops and Sheridan's forces., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 4 October 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes commenting on the fighting in the Shenandoah Valley between Confederate and Union forces. He expresses concern for her wellbeing., 5 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 6 October 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes sending news of himself and others and of the army's preparations. He mentions an attempted Union raid on the salt works in southwestern Virginia., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 16 October 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes sending news of himself, commenting on the army, and stating that he misses her., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 19 October 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes commenting on his life in the army., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 21 October 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes sending personal and family news. He also discusses the battle of Cedar Creek., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 26 October 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes commenting on his situation for rooms, the war, and personal news., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letters, 27 October 1864-11 Februart 1865 (Folder 4)
  - Letter, 27 October 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes discussing family and personal news and commenting on the army., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 4 November 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Augusta County, to Samuel Tynes, Tazewell County, concerning the health of Achilles' wife Harriet and where she will live during the winter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 4 November 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes concerning her accomodations for the winter months. Also sends news about the war., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 19 November 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes concerning his move to new quarters, people he has met, and his routine. He also comments about where she will stay during winter., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 20 November 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes commenting on his quarter and routine. He metions his clothes and asks about his family., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 22 November 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes concerning deteriorating social conditions, wishing the war were over, and commenting on her situation for winter., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 27 November 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes regarding his health, news in her letters, and other family and personal news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 28 November 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes discussing his declining hopes to visit home, his health, and his hopes for a letter. He also comments about gathering supplies for the troops., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 1 December 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes discussing their marriage and his devotion to her. He was disappointed in not receiving a letter from Harriet. Tynes also mentions his military duties., 3 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 10 December 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes concerning the army, his duties gathering supplies, and other news., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 12 December 1864, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes concerning her letter and forgiving her for some action. He also metions that General John McCausland will be taking command of part of his old cavalry brigade., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 27 January 1865, from Achilles J. Tynes, Union, Monroe County, West Virginia, to Harriet Tynes stating that he has rejoined his old command. He also sends family news., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 31 January 1865, from Achilles J. Tynes, 16th Virginia Cavalry, Greenbrier County, West Virginia to Harriet Tynes stating that he misses her and their child. He mentions the Hampton Roads Peace Conference and hopes that it will lead to peace., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 7 February 1865, from Achilles J. Tynes, 16th Virginia Cavalry, Greenbrier County, to Harriet Tynes concerning his transfer from Lomax's Cavalry Division headquarter to the 16th Virginia. He also sends other news., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 11 February 1865, from Achilles J. Tynes, McCausland's Brigade, to Harriet Tynes stating he is disappointed in not receiving a letter from her and that he misses her. Tynes adds that there is a dispute between Generals McCausland and Lomax about him., leaves, negative photostats.
- Letters, 17 February 1865-1951 (Folder 5)
  - Letter, 17 February 1865, from Achilles J. Tynes, 16th Virginia Cavalry, Greenbrier County, to Harriet Tynes commenting on the cold and snowy weather and mentioning other aspects of camp life., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 5 March 1865, from Achilles J. Tynes, Lexington, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes informing her of Early's defeat at the battle of Waynesboro. He describes his trip from Monroe County to Lexington, including meeting relatives and a narrow miss from drowning., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 15 September 1910, from William S. Grimes, Wapello, Iowa, to Achilles J. Tynes, Tazewell County, commenting on Grimes' service in the 26th Virginia Battalion., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 1 November 1950, from W. Edwin Hemphill, Virginia State Library, Richmond, Virginia, to Buford C. Tynes, Huntington, West Virginia, concerning the ride of Molly Tynes 17-18 July 1863 to warn people in Tazewell County of Toland's Raid on the area., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 3 November 1950, Buford C. Tynes, Huntington, to W. Edwin Hemphill, Richmond, concerning the ride of Molly Tynes and the possibilty of mapping it., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 15 May 1951, from Buford C. Tynes, Huntington, to Achilles L. Tynes, Staunton, Virginia, concerning the Kanawha Valley during the Civil War, their father Achilles J. Tynes, and a proposed visit by Buford Tynes to Staunton., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, n.d., from [Achilles J. Tynes] to [Harriet Tynes?] describing a fight between Confederate and Union forces., 2 leaves, incomplete, negative photostats.
  - Letter, n.d., from Achilles J. Tynes to [Harriet Tynes} concerning military life., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, n.d., from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes concering clothes that Tynes wants., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, n.d., from [Achilles J. Tynes] to [Harriet Tynes?] concerning military matters, stating that he has seen a relative, and informing her that he has frostbitten toes., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Envelope, n.d., addressed to Harriet Tynes, Tazewell C.H. Virginia., 2 leaves, 2 copies, negative photostats.